[Music]
the following is a production of Frankie
Freitas and the internet Museum of
geography
hello this is Frankie Freitas and
welcome to holotalk the internet's laser
and holography talk show our toll-free
number is
1-800-458-3525 or you can send an email
to holotalk
helloworld.com we've got telephone calls
we've got emails we've got special
guests coming up so thank you for tuning
in and let's get this week's show on the
road
hello and welcome to another week of
holotalk Deb how are you this week I'm
fine fine how are you I'm doing okay do
you know that we're live right now on
the internet
sorry and we're going to start again
do you know that we're live right now on
the internet
yes I know that
uh people are logging when we have a
webcam in the studio and we're uploading
the image to our website and people are
logging on and watching us right now
can't hear anything you won't be able to
hear anything until the show Sunday
night when the show is
uploaded in real audio format which
you're listening to right now but they
can see us uh might as well wave and say
hello to everybody hi out there in
Internet land
last week's show was 48 minutes long
that was long that was long I don't
think we're going to do any more 48
minute shows we can't tell how long the
show is
because we actually record this in bits
and pieces then we go into editing
programs and edit things out edit things
in and put it all together and we don't
know until the show's over how long it
is and we worked on that probably three
or four hours last week didn't we yeah I
think it was about three yeah and when
it was all finished uh came out to 48
minutes which is a pretty long time for
show I don't think we're going to go 48
minutes anymore I'd like to keep it
around a half an hour half an hour is
not a bad time you think that's a good
time but what do you do just like cut it
off yeah we had a lot of questions last
week we had to cover them and we've got
a lot of questions this week we probably
won't get two all of them because we
have our guests this week which is Paul
Graham he's from a company called light
vision you're going to have Paul Graham
on for an interview you remember about
Paul yeah I do he's the one with the
lollipops the one with the lollipops
they put holographic images on Lollipops
and other candies and edible items
musical guest this week is Emily toy box
and we're going to try something
different because this is just a voice
broadcast we we send this out so that
it's available over 14-4 modems
it's good for voice you have no problem
with receiving a signal and hearing a
voice with fairly good quality in 14-4
but once you get to the music 14 4
sounds like
not good do do
do you do so what we're doing is I'm
going to combine two files this first
one you're listening to is going to be
coming at you at 14 4 keeps the file
size small but as soon as Emily's Toy
Box comes up it's going to switch over
to 28 8.
the thing I'm interested to see is some
people have 14 4 modems other people
have 28 8. the 28 8 people should be
able to get both and I'm hoping that the
14-4 people can get the first part of
the show but yet when the music comes up
it may cut off for them so we'll have to
see how that works out if you have a
14-4 modem and you're listening to this
let us know how it works out when it
changes over to 2080. so the possibility
it may cut them off and they won't be
able to receive that signal
okay
what's up for tonight why don't we go to
an email question and
then we'll get moving okay
I have a 10 milliwatt laser and I was
wondering how hot the laser head should
get mine is very hot to touch is this
normal
if it's if it's uncomfortable to touch
it with your hand I'd have to say that
it's hotter than it should be
um you should always let the laser head
warm up before you do a hologram because
you're allowing it to reach thermal
stability
but once that laser head warms up it
shouldn't be anywhere near where where
it would feel very hot to the touch I
picked up a thermometer at Radio Shack
and this is an indoor outdoor
thermometer and what I do is I have that
thermometer on the wall next to the
laser and there's a probe and you use
this probe in normal circumstances by
putting it out your window so that you
can tell what the outside temperature is
what I did is I took the probe and I got
one of those metal collars that you can
buy over at the hardware store
sort of like holds hoses a hose clamp I
think is what it's called
and you can see it has a screw on it you
can make it Tighter and Tighter it makes
the collar smaller and smaller well I
slip that over the laser head
I put the little temperature probe
underneath of it and then I screw that
down so that the temperature probe is
touching the laser head itself this way
I can tell number one how hot the laser
head's getting and I can watch the
temperature and see when it finally
reaches a point where it's not rising or
dropping anymore that means of course
that the laser has reached thermal
stability the temperature that I usually
see on there I believe is 101 degrees
now that's not very hot that's
tepid that's probably like bath water
right yeah so if you're grabbing hold of
that laser head uh more than likely yeah
this is what's wrong if you have one of
the brick power supplies I would look on
that power supply and you're going to
see a little
potentiometer which is on there it's
actually something that you would need a
it almost looks like a screwdriver
adjustment but it's a very very tiny
screwdriver adjustment you may have to
use something like an exacto blade or
even a fingernail to turn that around
and what you do is you try to get that
adjusted so that you turn that into
counterclockwise position after the
laser is warmed up
and a counterclockwise position just
until the laser starts to sputter and
you'll see it sputtering it it happens
very rapidly with the beam once you see
that laser head sputter then you turn it
with your finger or your exacto blade or
whatever you're using just a little bit
past that point my guess is you've got
that turned up too much where you've got
one of the high power power supplies
that's powering one of the lower laser
head and you're feeding too much voltage
into it so you want to try and get that
voltage down that's going to drop down
your temperature and you don't want to
pump too much voltage into that laser
head because it will kill your laser
head before it's time for it to go you
should get twenty thousand hours of
working time out of that head we're
going to move on
to the interview segment you know why
why
do you ever see on TV that a special
program is going to be on with someone
that you really like and they tell you
to tune in at 10 o'clock right you tune
in at 10 o'clock and you sit there for a
half an hour 45 minutes or more before
the person comes on right we're not in
two seconds we're not going to do that
here we're not going to do that we
hold you in such a high regard as an
audience that we're not going to make
you sit through a whole show in order to
wait for the guests so what we're going
to do on the weeks when we have a guest
is we're going to get that guest on as
soon as possible
that's a good thing to do because that's
the way that we are
so we're going to go ahead with the Paul
Graham interview Paul's with a company
called light vision and light vision is
putting holographic images
presently on Lollipops but from what I
understand and what you'll hear in the
interview they're also going to be
putting it on other edible items as well
now light vision has a website
that website is
www.lightvision.com
and I just want to let you know that
with the real audio player and this is
the reason why I chose real audio
there's a number of different streaming
audio techniques out there with the real
audio player you don't have to stay
right where you're at and listen to the
show
just open your browser again bring it to
the Forefront because the player is
probably in the front now just click on
your browser bring it to the front
and put in
www.lightvision.com and next thing you
know you're over at light vision but hey
the interview's still playing other
systems if you go off the page
it stops the audio but you can go
anywhere you want to and enjoy Holo talk
while you're while you're out there so
let's go to Paul Graham and the
interview that we did what was it in the
beginning of the week probably around 10
30 at night well I was late okay here we
go Paul Graham
okay we're speaking with Paul Graham of
the company like Vision Paul how are you
good good Frank how are you okay it's
great to have you on the show I just
want to let you know I have one of your
pops already that I use in my
demonstration that I do at the center
and everyone just loves them when they
see them oh that's fantastic which which
part do you have I have the one that was
for the Nova television series on PBS oh
no but that was one of the that was one
of our first clients actually that's a
fabulous pop what are some of the other
companies that you're doing these
holographic pops for before we get into
the actual pops themselves yeah we do we
tend to specialize in some custom work
at the moment because the company is
only about a year old so when
only movie to retail but some of the
other companies we've worked with have
been the New York Times with the premium
choice in New York Times at the moment
which is great for us uh we're doing a
pop for Disney featuring Mickey Mouse uh
doing some work the universal have done
some work for KLM
also for Bach and love as well the eye
care company and a few smaller sort of
Technology Cutting Edge technology
companies that most people aren't aware
of that sort of more regionally based at
the present time where could they go to
get one and where do you expect them to
be able to go to get one in the future
what we're doing is that we've we've
only just this week actually launched
our retail items we've had a Star Trek
collectors box in holography stores for
about the last nine months which is a
four pack of Star Trek images we've just
released our single pops this week uh
the best place I would suggest
immediately would be to get it off our
website we have ordering on our website
but
eventually most of the science centers
and some of the Science stores like I
expect like um kid McDougall and and
places like that and Toys R Us
eventually it'll it'll turn very quickly
and they'll be there are a few catalogs
also
um we're actually in the wild catalog at
the moment with the Star Trek item uh
the Johnson Smith Company and the things
that you never knew existed were coming
into the upcoming catalog for January
and I'm also going on Home Shopping
Channel very soon in the next flight
come on tune in to see that yeah no
definitely that should be pretty
interesting I'm kind of nervous about it
actually that one catalog that you
mentioned about and things that you
never knew existed I just got one of
those last week and normally catalogs
hit the trash quickly in this house and
I still have that one I still hold on to
that catalog interesting stuff in there
we're also talking a Sharper Image as
well so I mean it's I think fairly
quickly you're going to be able to see
this product available because most
people are fascinated with it it's
pretty fascinating product what's what's
the retail on these Pops in some of the
shops
um I'll forget to retail ranges from
about 295 to 350 depending on uh the
store some stores tend to want a little
bit more than other stores
and it's but we're planning to bring the
price down fairly quickly as well we're
basically going for a little bit of
Technology curve at the moment so I
expect them to be available for about a
dollar fifty next year now the Star Trek
ones are actually in a pack of four yeah
the Star Trek collectors box it's a it's
a good box there's a limited edition of
25 000 it comes with four pops and a
certificate a holographic certificate of
authenticity and uh there's an image of
Picard Klingon the Enterprise and Star
Trek logo
without giving any secrets out that you
obviously have to hold on for your own
protection of doing this and inventing
this technology with you know your
company uh
would you tell some of the listeners
what goes into putting a holographic
image on a lollipop
um yes I can um well basically the
history of the Hologram was that it was
invented by a physicist at uh MIT his
name is Eric Baker and Eric is actually
a principal of our company uh he
actually still handles all the
holography work for us Erica discovered
that he could impart images on the food
products so basically what he devised
was a system where he can cut little
tiny grooves in the surface of the food
what happens is the light comes in and
reflects off these grooves and forms an
image in your eye just just the way
things happen with sort of like an
embossed hologram basically it's a very
similar sort of process
you're able to do this with uh Pops I
believe because something to do with the
sucrose or something being almost like a
plastic yeah basically I mean basically
most food most Foods
um like flour starches and sugars
um I really thought natural form of
plastic I mean they're not a stable form
but they effectively work like a plastic
I mean glasses as you know with embossed
Holograms deforming
um glass is actually also sort of like a
plastic type agent so Eric sort of
postulated that he could use food
similar to uh using metals or glass or
anything else and um it tends to work
when I share the parts during my demo I
always get a question can you eat them
and it's of course you can eat them
um and then the next question is all
well what's in them you know that makes
the image there and there's nothing in
them at all yeah that's I think that's
the most unique thing about the product
is that
um it is very there's nothing at it
they're all the color all the color
comes from life but what you're seeing
is you're thinking like a full 3d how in
some cases some of the images actually
move a little bit
but it's just being
illustrated by the Light uh some some
common mistakes that people try and do
they try and look through the Hologram
and this is very much light activated
the brighter the light on the
holographic pop the sharper the brighter
the image is going to be but there is
nothing at it it's a totally natural
process and that's something uh even
being involved with light vision that I
sometimes sort of sit back and sit back
as amazed that but this this process
doesn't doesn't involve any colorings or
additives so if there's no FDA
regulations it's a very safe and natural
process now someone on the company may
had a logo that they'd like to have on
the part they can contact you and have
that logo placed on the pop right
totally that that we are very uh we
specialize in custom work we've had most
of the people who've done work with us
have reordered they've been very happy
with the response the interesting thing
about doing custom work is that most
people have and you probably see from
your classes rank I mean most people
have never seen this before
Holograms still people haven't seen
regular Holograms that come to come
through Center oh they there you go so
um the fact that you can Aid it most of
the counties tend to use it for trade
shows and things for cutting through the
Clutter and premiums and from that
perspective it's exciting that yes we
definitely offer that Services very
reasonably priced
um you know we're really in the business
to try and get the usage available
Holograms out to the public and uh we're
very excited about the opportunities
that are coming our way now I know a lot
of companies that take advantage of this
but I would imagine if there were
someone who just had a recent birth in
the family and they had a photo of their
little girl or boy that was just born
they could think of the baby's picture
put on pops and have pops manufactured
oh that yeah and that's for the price of
course yeah for the price and we um
we've done a few bomb mixes and we've
done a wedding so far so that's very
possible and they have very very unique
thing and I think that that will
probably do more of that in the future
that's something that I think will go
into
specialize in at some stage I I visited
your website which is very well done and
I'd recommend anyone to jump over there
especially after you finish listening to
Holo talk and you close out your real
audio player or even while you're
listening to the interview itself
because from what I understand the real
audio player will play in the background
as you continue to surf the web
know or unless there's a little bit
about your website and what they can
find when they go on to the site itself
basically what we've tried to do with
the life of the website is to educate
people
um we have sections that feature some of
our retail products our new retail
products and that's the Dr hologram
brand
I should I should really we had just
released this new brand and Dr hologram
is our Flagship brand and he is like
this inventor that we've invented and
we're hoping to do some great things
with him and I think he's probably going
to be a cross between uh Indiana Jones
and uh Doc Brown from
Back to the Future people can also order
these pops you know the holidays are
coming up and what what better gift
could you give someone or as a stocking
stuffer than to take one of these
holographic lollipops and put them in
stockings for Christmas yeah we
had as well but and actually that's what
a lot of people do I think for um it's a
great stocking stuffer
um we also have like a fair range of
information about how the Holograms work
uh we have a practical guide to
holography
we also have a library which has like a
fairly extensive sort of linking
mechanism to most of the major
holographic sites and I think we have
your site on that I have to prefer that
yes I think it's in there somewhere yeah
I also want to mention that practical
holography manual that you have on the
site is excellent and I know there's a
lot of it's science fair time across the
country there's a lot of kids that are
sending emails to me and I'm sure other
holographers that are listening that
have sites are getting emails as well as
far as how can I get more information
about holography well if you're
listening to this broadcast go to
www.lightvision.com and you will find a
link there called practical holography
and it's a wonderful tutorial on
holography itself which is which is very
nice for you to offer that to the public
to come through and see that well we I
mean we obviously like to educate the
the public on what we're doing and this
is something that Eric put together on
these holographic images 3D or are they
the basically 2D 3D type of creation
that you see on some of the stickers the
they tend to be 2D 3D they're more dot
matrix than they are hoe later we can do
hoe the trouble is that what we've found
for most of the clients that we're
working with is you need to you need to
get a glimmer or something
um the hole works very well you can get
a very 3d full depth image but but when
we're doing trade show work we want to
get something that people actually see
something straight away so they're not
thinking that they uh the best way to do
that is with the 2D 3D because if you're
a diffraction that's taking place is
happening within the plane of the
Hologram itself you don't have to worry
about any sort of smear you know with
any depth like you have with the typical
hologram if you were to pull it out on a
convention floor
you'd find out that unless you were
right under one of those sodium vapor
lights or anything that were up on the
convention ceiling unless you were right
under them you'd notice that you'd have
either multiple images or you'd have
smeared images exactly it just would not
work but with your Technique it doesn't
it pretty much doesn't matter where you
would be standing you're always going to
get a nice effect from that hologram
yeah and that and that's what we but we
are learning we are moving to work on
from uh to get a lot more depth and a
lot more motion we're also moving to put
it on other Foods we have um we have a
chocolate we're working on chocolate
right now
um I have put like
images onto Pop Tarts but we also have a
holographic dust that we can put onto
cereals and cookies and you can bake
with which gives a glitter effect and
that's a fairly unique sort of item that
we've been working on is this this is a
diffraction grating that's actually
etched right into the dust itself yes
yes that's exactly it and when it comes
absolutely incredible
anything else you want to let our
listeners know about
um no that's about it I you know I wish
everyone well for the holidays upcoming
holidays and uh looking forward to
people dropping by outside okay well we
wish you well and uh thank you for being
a guest on whole talk we really
appreciate it that's what keeps the show
going
back to hear what all the people in the
field of Photography are doing and uh
good luck with the pops and I'm looking
forward to seeing them out on the store
shelves I'm looking forward to walking
around the mall and seeing someone
actually eating one there you go
through you that'll make my day okay
Paul thank you very much
there we have the Paul Graham interview
what did you think of that Deb I thought
it was really interesting I think I'd
really enjoy some of that chocolate okay
I didn't enjoy the chocolate too and the
dust that sounds like it would make some
interesting anything cakes cookies
anything for the holidays I think I'd
like to have the holographic dust on all
my birthday cakes from now on we'll see
what we can do okay let's move on to a
news item now we'll grab one news item
one email and then we're gonna head out
of here for this week okay okay and then
of course we have Emily's toy box coming
up as our musical guest this week so you
want to hold on for that so let's go to
our news item
okay
you're on I'm on okay
okay for real okay a group from Sri
International in Menlo Park California
has demonstrated an optical storage
method for page formatted Digital Data
based on time domain holography this is
a technique that could allow high
performance input and output of data to
an optical storage system Digital Data
Pages were generated by Illuminating a
spatial light modulator with 11.2
microsecond Pulses from a ring Dye Laser
operating at about 580 nanometers
stored by wavelength division
multiplexing in a distinct channel of
about 500 kilohertz within a seven
millimeter thick Crystal
after recording data were retrieved at a
peak rate of 300 megabits per second
without the use of error correcting
codes
using a detection scheme for the
extraction of binary data the system raw
bit error rate was 10 to 7 meaning the
10 megabits of data could be stored
without generating an error this was
demonstrated by the team using a black
and white photograph of Albert Einstein
okay Deb thank you very much for that
very interesting and informative story
that is the future of data storage
people holographic data storage storing
information inside of photorefractive
crystals using lasers
let's go to one more email question and
we're going to move on to Emily's toy
box
okay the last one that we have here is
do lasers come in different colors other
than red okay let's not tell a fib well
not the last one the last one we're
going to do okay this is the one we have
yes as you know every other week
we have a guest and that guest show has
less questions on it and then every
other week it falls in the middle of the
other every other week
we do
we catch up on the questions there we go
okay so we're going to do the one more
and that question is again okay do
lasers come in different colors other
than red Frank okay
that's a very simple question but it's a
very common question because most people
only see helium neon lasers a lot of
times kids in school they have helium
neon laser there they want to know the
lasers come in other colors as well yes
they do
and it all depends on the actual medium
that's being waived
for instance a helium neon laser is a
gas laser
and it produces a red beam or I should
say a
primarily a red beam you can also Force
other wavelengths out as well such as
green and yellow but if you have a 10
milliwatt red laser
that same 10 milliwatt red laser would
probably only give you a one milliwatt
green and yellow because they're a much
less powerful line
that that gas produces to line meaning
wavelength argon lasers which has Argon
gas in it produces blue green beams and
you can pass that beam through a prism
and actually extract those colors out of
that beam
and so on and so forth with the
different gases that are in the laser so
to answer your question yes lasers come
in many different colors they also
generate beams that are not part of the
visible spectrum they can generate beams
which are in the infrared part of the
spectrum where you cannot see the beam
with the human eye they also generate
beams at the opposite end of the
spectrum up into the ultraviolet and
even on into the X-ray part of the
Spectrum which once again cannot be
detected with the eye so yes they do
produce many different colors than red
and they also produce much more than
that
well Deb that about wraps it up for a
week I hope we're close to 30 minutes
but I think we're probably going to be
over again really I think we maybe be
under really we'll have to see let's see
next week we'll let you know okay were
we over as I feel we are or were we
under as I feel we were okay
we're goofy tonight I'll tell you what
we have we were broadcasting live on the
internet with a webcam and I brought I
have studio lights in here which are
probably about
of 2 000 Watts total and I think the
heat has to be up to at least 100
degrees in here possibly possibly 100
degrees so so let's go to our musical
guest this week it's Emily's toy box and
their CD it's titled I never get my way
they have a website it's
www.emilistoybox.com and Emily is
spelled e-m-i-l-y-f
emilystoybox.com they're from Carlisle
PA
they're a really funny band they have
crazy stage Antics which has
created quite a following for them we're
going to select
two titles off of the CD title number
one will be don't say no and title
number two will be term paper so we'll
be hearing from Emily's toy box
and before I go hold on
where are my papers and I should be
prepared but I'm not
but I know it's here somewhere
no it's not
well I'll tell you I was going to go
down the list of guests that we have
coming up
and I was born in 1956 in Philadelphia
Pennsylvania
and I grew up
I found it okay
okay so we're on November 23rd which is
Paul Graham from light vision December
7th Wang Chun from holographic
development company in China
musical guest Junoon we won't go on with
the musical guests we'll just go down
with December 21st Eric gallon from the
Royal holographic gallery
January 4th Alex Schmitz I hope I'm
pronouncing that right Alex we've sent
email back and forth quite a few times
but I've never found out how to
correctly say your last name I hope I'm
doing it right but I'm sure I'll find
out the night you're on and he's with
three deep company and what they do is
they're importing the Russian emotions
for people who are doing Holograms and
they're finding a hard time to get
anything from agffa because agfa has
stopped production
January 18th excuse me last week on the
show we said we couldn't mention who the
guest was because we're still in
negotiation with it that has been
completed and our guest will be Dr
Stephen Benton and we will have him on
for a rundown on what to expect at
photonics West 98 that's Dr Stephen
Benton
January 18 1998 February 1st Brian
Monahan from Pennsylvania Pulp and Paper
and they do desktop holography I guess
it would be fair to call it
desktopolography it's actually a much
more complex setup than just a simple
term like desktop holography but Brian
will bring us up to date on what that's
all about
February 15th Jimmy Wilford and he has a
company which does security Holograms in
Panama the country Panama
and I know we're booked up until April
but my list only goes to February 15th
so what I'm going to do is probably put
those names up on the website
okay so thank you for tuning in as
always Deb thank you for being here with
us my pleasure couldn't do without you
that's my sidekick Deb
science has discovered
secret of the atom and it has found out
the expanse of the universe
but the mind has not yet been born that
could comprehend the deepness of our
thank you for tuning in here comes
Emily's toy box